<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The near approach of Christ's kingdom, clearly proved by Scripture with a certain account of the signs of the present times relating thereto ...</title>
            <author>Marsin, M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M813C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15700</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13146890</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13146890</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98071</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 428:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The near approach of Christ's kingdom, clearly proved by Scripture with a certain account of the signs of the present times relating thereto ...</title>
                  <author>Marsin, M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.M., and are to be sold by Tho. Fabian ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: M.M.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to M. Marsin. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Appears also in: The first book. 1698.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Kingdom.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98071:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98071:1"/>
            <p>THE Near Aproach of CHRIST's KINGDOM, Clearly proved by Scripture.</p>
            <p>With a certain Account of the Signs of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Times relating thereto.</p>
            <p>As alſo, That the Converſion and Reſtauration of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be after the Lord's coming.</p>
            <p>That after the Lord's coming, moſt of the great Plagues mentioned in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> will be poured out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth, and the Wicked.</p>
            <p>That the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet will be then taken alive.</p>
            <p>That all the Chriſtians that came in by Chriſt of the Gentile Race, were termed Heathens, in the Old Teſtament. And that the Law and Goſpel ſpeaks but to them that are under it.</p>
            <q>That after the Fiery Tempeſt, the Heavens and Earth will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd, and all things reſtored as in the beginning.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>M. M.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Fabian,</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> in <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel And divers other Bookſellers about <hi>London.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:98071:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>The moſt material points that we are in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie about, are already anſwered, which Books are to be ſold at the ſame Bookſellers, and of a ſmall price, that thereby they may be the eaſier had by all. There will other Books come forth in a ſhort time, ſo as by Gods aſſiſtance, all the diſputable places, and moſt of the figurative ſpeeches will be by the word it ſelf, fully and clearly explained.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 48. <hi>l.</hi> 27. from the top, <hi>r.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.12.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98071:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KING, AND Parliament.</head>
            <p>THIS Treatiſe giving an Account of the <hi>Certain Signs of the Times,</hi> and the <hi>near approach of the coming of the Lord,</hi> is humbly preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That they may know what God is going about to do, ſo as to prepare for the coming of Chriſt. 'Tis therefore moſt humbly hoped our moſt Gracious King, with the Great Council of the Nation, who have ſo wonderfully appeared for the Defence of the Proteſtant Religion, may be further inſtrumental to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, in encouraging the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truths herein contained. God grant His Majeſty to be a Bleſſing to the Nations till the Lord comes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98071:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN I heard of thoſe often repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Earthquakes, the like where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the World never produced; and that it is according to the Word of the Lord that there ſhould be Earthquakes in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, with diſtreſs of Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when theſe things come to paſs; the Lord hath bidden ſuch as have an Intereſt in him, then to look up, and to lift up their heads, for their Redemption draweth nigh, <hi>Luke 21 28.</hi> The thoughts of which, ſet me on a fervent longing deſire for the coming of the Lord, and drew out my heart in more ardent deſires after him; whereupon I took to the Lord's direction, reſolving to ſearch the Scriptures with more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence than ever I had done; the which I no ſooner had performed, but I found the certainty of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord, and that it was very nigh at hand; but ſtill I was to ſeek how, and in what manner; for I could then no ways make the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament agree, neither did I then rightly underſtand any of the figurative ſpeeches; and finding it too
<pb facs="tcp:98071:3"/>hard for me, I was much troubled thereat; but as I had taken to the Lords direction in the ſearch of the Scripture, whereby I came to the aſſured know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his coming; ſo I alſo would, according to the advice therein, ſeek to the Lord for knowledge to underſtand the ſecrets therein contained, as <hi>Prov. 2.3, 4, 5, 6.</hi> for he is <hi>the wonderful Counſellor, and the mighty God,</hi> Iſa. <hi>9.6.</hi> The which, when I ſo did, the Lord more and more inlightened my underſtanding in his Word: So as I do wholly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the diſcovery of theſe great and hidden Myſteries was from the Lord, and attained according to the way directed in his Word, which is by prayer and diligence.</p>
            <p>This ſmall Treatiſe, being an Eſſay, containeth the plain Heads eaſie to the apprehenſion of any, that thereby all theſe great things might the better be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in their memory, ſo as to ſink down upon the heart. The other Book, being ſomewhat more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult for them to underſtand, that are not well vers'd in the Word, and underſtand not the way of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaking: For therein is moſt of the figurative ſpeeches opened by the Key of the Word; that is, by joyning Scripture to Scripture, and in not leaving any other Scriptures to contradict what is ſaid; whereby the true meaning of the Word is clearly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. But theſe great Myſteries were to remain a ſecret to the time of the end, according to the Word of the Lord in <hi>Daniel, chap. 12.4.</hi> And in <hi>Zech. 14.7.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>It ſhall come to paſs, that at evening time it ſhall be light.</hi> And in that God has made choice of ſo weak an Inſtrument, it is
<pb facs="tcp:98071:4"/>that his power might the more eminently appear therein; and that the Infinite God hath now at this evening time cauſed the true meaning of his Word to be diſcovered; it is an infallible Sign of the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain near approach of the coming of the Lord; for whoſe coming, if we prepare, we ſhall be certainly happy; but if you will put the day far off, it will then come on you as a ſnare, <hi>Luke ch. 21.</hi> v. <hi>34, 35.</hi> in which you will be deſtroyed; but if you will be as earneſt with God for your ſelves, and ſo continue, as I have been earneſt with the Almighty for the generality of you all; I make no question but you will be for ever bleſſed; for if we will not be wanting to our ſelves, God will not be wanting to us: Now that we, and the generality of the Christian World, would ſeek the Lord, whilst he is to be found; and that the Warnings he gives us to prepare for his coming, might ſo awaken us, as that we may be found with our Lamps trimmed, and our Lights burning, is the earnest prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>M. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98071:4"/>
            <head>A certain Account of the Signs of the Laſt Times. The Coming of the Lord. The Deſtruction of <hi>Babylon:</hi> With the Chriſtians that remain in their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs. Alſo the Calling in of the Jews. And the Reſtoration of all things.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. I.</hi> A neceſſity of being ready prepared for the Lord's Coming; leſt that Day ſhould come upon us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, which is very near at hand.</head>
               <p>NOW we, not apprehending the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition that we ſtand in, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we falſly imagine that the New Everlaſting Covenant is made with us; when now the Believers are but Heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of the ſame Promiſe; but becauſe Chriſt ſaid of them that were given him of his Father, to be his ſtanding Witneſſes thro' the World, that none ſhould pluck them out of his hand. And the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Churches that firſt truſted in Chriſt, which had the abundant pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings forth of the Spirit upon them to ſecure their ſtanding, and thereby they generally ſtood; which in Scripture, the <hi>major</hi> part is reckoned for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98071:5"/>whole. And the Spirit was alſo given to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Goſpel to the World, and the following Generations, as will be abundantly proved; but we having been in a miſtake as to theſe things, have thought it no concern of ours to know whether the Lord is coming or not. But we alſo by miſunderſtanding the words of the Lord, when he ſent forth his Diſciples to teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſaying, <hi>He that believeth ſhall be ſaved.</hi> That is, they that believed the Doctrine which Chriſt ſent them forth to teach; in which was included the conditions of man's ſalvation, the which, whoſoever accordingly believed, ſhould be ſaved; and they which believed not, ſhould be damned. Now theſe words were but of force to them that believed, and to them that refuſed believing; for unto whom the Word never came, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be damned for not believing that which they never heard. And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>That what things ſoever the Law ſaith, it ſaith to them who are under the Law, Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12. So likewiſe what the Goſpel ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under the Goſpel, that is, to them that have the Goſpel, and obey, or refuſe to obey the ſame; to them accordingly does the promiſed mercies, or otherwiſe the threatned judgments belong. And tho' St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that hath the Son, hath life; and he that hath not the Son, hath not life,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.12. Yet theſe words do not exclude all them which have never heard of the Son, ſo as that none of them ſhould ever have life by the Son; for there will be a Redemption
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98071:5"/>in the World to come, as will be proved. And when Chriſt comes to judge the World, and at the laſt and final Judgment, they are all ſaid to be judged according to the deeds done in the body, whether they have been good or evil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.35. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. <hi>James</hi> 1.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12, 13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18, 19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23, 26. And tho' in the Parable of the Sheep and the Goats, there is but two ſorts mentioned, yet there is a third included, in as much as the Poor, and Children, were not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to be made partakers of the Bleſſing, or the Curſe, in their doing, or not doing good to God's Elect: And therefore the word <hi>all,</hi> to them on his left hand, is not mentioned, when he ſentenced them to everlaſting fire, <hi>Matth. ch.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 41. And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>all Nations,</hi> it is but meant all the Nations that have the Goſpel. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord will come to take vengeance on them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8. The word <hi>all,</hi> he here mentions not, but he chiefly includes them that have the Knowledge of God, and of the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: For the Goſpel ſpeaks to them that have the Goſpel, yet in works deny it, in that they will not yield obedience to it. For it is declared in ſeveral places of Scripture, too many to be here ſet down, that the Jews will be called in, when the Lord again comes, and they do no ways obey the Goſpel, and then according to the word,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98071:6"/>the Lord he will gather in others with them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.8. Theſe things being abundantly proved in a Book that is coming forth, of which I ſhall here ſet down ſome few proofs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. II. <hi>The Reſtoration of</hi> Iſrael.</head>
               <p>THat the Reſtoration of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be at the time, when the Nations round about, are judged in the Valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat;</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Lord ſaith, <hi>Aſſemble your ſelves, and come up all ye heathen round about, Joel</hi> 3.11, 12. This is ſpoken to thoſe that have <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Land in their poſſeſſion, and unto them that are their Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: And the reaſon why they are termed Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, was becauſe there was no other then, but Jews and Heathen; and that then not only the back-ſliding Chriſtians, which were afore pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of, were ſo term'd, but alſo the beſt of Saints, that came in by Chriſt of the Gentile race, are likewiſe termed Heathen, as in 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 2.34. <hi>I ſay unto you, O ye Heathen, that hear and underſtand, look for your Shepherd, he ſhall give you everlaſting reſt.</hi> And what the Law and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſaith, it ſaith to thoſe that are under the Law and Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13, 14, 15. as Chriſtians and Turks: For the backſliding Chriſtians, are thoſe that are under the condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of the Law and Goſpel; and alſo the Turks acknowledge the true God, but in Works deny him, and therefore fall under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning power of the Moral Law. And whereas the Lord ſaith, <hi>Come up all ye Heathen, Joel</hi> 3.2.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98071:6"/>now the word <hi>all,</hi> in Scripture, doth not include the whole, and the Converſion of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will alſo be, <hi>When Saviours come upon Mount Sion, then the Kingdom will be the Lord's, Obad. v.</hi> 21. Then it is <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall <hi>ſee him whom they have pierced, and mourn over him, Zech.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. And after the Lord deſcends upon <hi>Mount Olivet, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> will be built, never more to be deſtroyed, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.10, 11. and the Wicked never more to have a prevailing power againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> And the Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That Jeruſalem ſhall be trodden down of the Gentiles, until the times of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles be fulfilled, Luke</hi> 21.24. Which ſhews the Gentile Power will be wholly taken away be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> will be reſtored.</p>
               <p>Accordingly St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where he ſpeaks of the Converſion of the Jews, turns them to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> where the Lord is there declared to come to judge the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.17, 18, 19, 20. and God by the ſame Prophet, ordered Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to the end of this world, <hi>Say ye to the daughter of Sion, behold thy Salvation cometh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his reward is with him, Iſa.</hi> 62.11. Which ſhews, their Salvation is not to be, till the time of the power of this wicked world is ended; and therefore it is ſaid, when the Lord comes, that the Beaſt, and falſe Prophet will be taken alive, and caſt into a lake of fire burning with brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ſo as time for them, and the wicked of this World, ſhall be no longer, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Paul</hi> bids the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.18, 19. <hi>Do good, that they be rich in good works, ready to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98071:7"/>diſtribute, willing to communicate, laying up in ſtore for themſelves, a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternal life.</hi> Thereby ſhewing there is another time after this time, before Eternity, in which the Saints will be bleſſed, and then it is that <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be <hi>ſaved with an everlaſting ſalvation,</hi> If. 45.17. the which will be at the time of the reſtoration of all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20, 21, 22. <hi>And he ſhall ſend Jeſus Christ, which before was preached unto you: Whom the Heaven must receive, until the times of the restitution of all things, which God hath ſpoken by the mouth of all his Prophets ſince the world began. For Moſes truly ſaid unto the Fathers, A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, of your Brethren, like unto me; him ſhall ye hear in all things whatſoever he ſhall ſay unto you.</hi> And now is this Scripture ready to be fulfilled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. III.</hi> The Coming of the Lord.</head>
               <p>SAint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16, 17. <hi>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from heaven with a ſhout, with the voice of the Arch-angel, and with the trump of God; and the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt, then we which are alive, and rémain, ſhall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air, and ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lord.</hi> Whereas the Apoſtle here ſaith, we which are alive, all know, that in this (we) the wicked are not included; neither in this (we) are all the righteous then living included, but by this (we) he comprehends thoſe that were to bear their te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98071:7"/>to the Goſpel, as the firſt Churches did, and as the ſtanding witneſs hath continued to do; the which are thoſe who are ſaid to be clothed in Sackcloth, and lie in the ſtreet of the Great City, which is ſpiritually called <hi>Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8. and theſe are thoſe that are ſaid will be caught up in the clouds to meet the Lord in the Air, and theſe are the Elect that cry day and night unto him, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7. but the other Believers will be gathered, according as by the Lord is declared, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.34, 35. <hi>There ſhall be two men in one bed, the one ſhall be taken, and the other ſhall be left; two women ſhall be grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, the one ſhall be taken, and the other ſhalt be left.</hi> And the Lord ſaith, <hi>It will be as in the days of Lot.</hi> Whereby it doth alſo appear, that the other Believers will be lifted out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger by the Angels, as <hi>Lot</hi> was out of <hi>Sodom,</hi> whilſt the Wicked will be left, to receive part of their puniſhment here. And thoſe that are thus to be taken and gathered, are thoſe that have the Goſpel, and live in obedience thereunto. But as for <hi>Iſrael</hi> that now own not the Goſpel, they ſhall be called in, according as the Lord by the Prophets hath declared to them, (whoſe teſtimony they have received) and they likewiſe ſhall be brought to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as it is written, upon Horſes, and in Chariots, and in Litters, and upon Mules, and ſwift Beaſts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.6, 7, 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.20. And then it is, that <hi>with weeping and ſupplications, the Lord will lead them, Jer.</hi> 31.9. For the Lord will keep to his uſual way and method
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98071:8"/>in bringing them home, by a ſenſe of their own miſcarriage, before he giveth them the Holy Ghoſt. And tho' the Apoſtle ſaith of them that were choſen, to bear their teſtimony to the truth, that they ſhould at the coming of the Lord be changed in a moment, in the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an Eye: Yet the others that are then ſaved, will not then be ſo ſuddenly changed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will their natural body then, be changed into a ſpiritual body, but their natural body will be then healed of all infirmities, and their mind alſo, 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 6.26. And when their time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning will be, then will others of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, <hi>of all Languages of the Nations, take hold of the skirt of a</hi> Jew, <hi>ſaying, we will go with you, Zech.</hi> 8.23. For as there was a mixt multitude went out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo again when <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which will then be his Elect, <hi>Ro.</hi> 11.28. which will be gathered from the four winds, into which the Lord hath ſcattered them, then alſo there will a mixt multitude of the Heathen go with them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is ſaid. But the poor Chriſtians that have loſt their Day and Seaſon of Grace, will not be ſo permitted to do.</p>
               <p>And tho' at firſt the Lord will lead <hi>Iſrael</hi> with weeping, and ſupplications, yet alſo their return to <hi>Sion,</hi> will be with ſinging, <hi>and everlaſting joy ſhall be upon their heads; they ſhall obtain joy and gladneſs, and ſorrow and mourning ſhall flee away, Iſa.</hi> 58.11. And alſo it will be after the Lord comes, that moſt of thoſe great Plagues men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the <hi>Revelations</hi> will be poured forth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98071:8"/>upon the wicked of the Earth, ſo that according as it is ſaid, <hi>they ſhall gnaſh their teeth and melt away, Pſal.</hi> 112.10. after which will come the ſtorm mentioned in the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> of Hail, Fire, and <hi>Brimstone, which will be the portion of their Cup, Pſal.</hi> 11.6. and then, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Hail ſhall ſweep away the refuge of lies, Iſa.</hi> 28.17. Now this is ſpoken to them that have the word, for we are not permitted to judge them that are without, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. Now whereas St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>The heavens being on fire ſhall be diſſolved, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. Theſe words of the Apoſtle have a two-fold meaning, firſt, he hath an alluſion to the figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Heavens and Elements, which by fire will be diſſolved or burnt up; ſecondly, the Airy Heavens, and Material Earth, will be purged, or purified by the tempeſt of fire, ſo as the outward face of the Earth will be burnt up. And then again God will make all things new, at which time the raiſed Saints will be in the glorious Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and the Believers, and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and all the promiſed Elect, which the Lord will call in at his coming, will be ſecured in the Holy Land, and between <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> Zech. 14.4, 5. This is further proved by Scripture, and explained in the fore-mentioned Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. IV.</hi> Be ready for the Coming of the Lord.</head>
               <p>WO to the Chriſtians that ſhall be found in darkneſs at that day, and tho' Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Of that day and hour knoweth no man, Mark</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98071:9"/>13.32. But however, he hath left upon record the certain Signs of the times, which when they are ſeen, he bids ſuch as have an intereſt in him, <hi>lift up their heads and look up, for their Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion draweth nigh,</hi> Lu. 21.28. thereby ſhewing that all that expect to have an intereſt in him, muſt prepare for him. For it was thoſe that would not take the warning, both in the Old World, and in the time of <hi>Lot,</hi> that were deſtroyed. And alſo the Lord ſaid of the Jews, that they <hi>were a wicked and adulterous generation, which could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the face of the sky, but could not diſcern the ſigns of the times, Matth.</hi> 16.3. The which became de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to them; but St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ye are not in darkneſs, that that day ſhould come upon you at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.4. And bleſſed will they be, that upon the warning the Lord gives them, will ſo prepare for him, as to have their Lamps trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and their lights burning. For the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth himſelf to a man <hi>that took a long journey, and gave to every man his work and commanded the Porter to watch. And the Lord ſaith, watch ye therefore, leſt coming ſuddenly, I find you ſleeping, Mark</hi> 13.34, 35, 36, 37. Theſe places ſhew the dreadful condition thoſe Chriſtians will be in, that will not take warning by the Signs given by him; and the Lord alſo ſaith, <hi>If the good man of the houſe had known what hour the Thief would have come, he would have watched, and not have ſuffered his houſe to have been broken through, Luke</hi> 12.39. For as the Thief comes to deſtroy, ſo the Lord will come to the deſtruction of them that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98071:9"/>profeſs they know him, yet will not make prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. V.</hi> The Signs of the Times.</head>
               <p>NOW as concerning the Time, and the Signs of the Time; that is, that the time of the Signs and Wonders, to the time of Chriſt's coming, and afterwards, till ſuch time as the Wicked are taken off from the Earth, it doth clearly appear, will be forty five years; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which time <hi>Iſrael</hi> lay in the Wilderneſs, and were Conquering their Enemies in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> before they were peaceably ſetled there; for in numbers it is ſaid, <hi>According to this time, it ſhall be ſaid of Jacob and of Iſrael, what hath God wrought? Numb.</hi> 23.23. The like is ſaid in <hi>Micah, According to the days of thy coming out of the land of Egypt, I will ſhew unto him marvellous things, the nations ſhall be confounded at all their might, Mich</hi> 7.15, 16. And it is ſaid in <hi>Zechary,</hi> 14.3. <hi>Then ſhall the Lord go forth and fight againſt thoſe nations, as when he fought in the day of battel.</hi> And in <hi>Daniel</hi> there is juſt forty five days difference in the number of the days, and he is ſaid to be bleſſed that comes to the laſt number, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.12. And that we are now far gone in this forty five days of years, is certain, by the Signs of the Times; and if they began in 1663. when the great Blazing Star appeared, which the Aſtronomers ſaid was a Rod to whip the Earth withal: And ſince we have had Signs in the Sun, and in the Moon, and oft repeated
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98071:10"/>Blazing Stars, according to the Word of the Lord, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.25. or whether the beginning of the limited time was, when the Evil Spirits mentioned in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> Chap. 16. 13, 14 came <hi>out of the mouth of the dragon, and out of the mouth of the beaſt, and out of the mouth of the falſe prophet, which has gathered together the Kings of the earth, to the battel of the great day of God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> And by theſe the World is now in an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roar, as in, 2 <hi>Eſdras</hi> 9.3, 4. and alſo the Lord ſaith in <hi>Luke,</hi> Chap. 21.25, 26, 27. <hi>There ſhall be diſtreſs of nations, with perplexity, the ſea and the waves thereof roaring, mens hearts failing them for fear, and looking after thoſe things which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the earth, for the powers of heaven ſhall be ſhaken.</hi> By which is meant the ruling powers of the earth, which in Scripture, is alſo called the Heavens. And then it is the Lord will come, as in <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>And then ſhall they ſee the Son of man coming in a cloud with power and great glory.</hi> And it is alſo given us as a Sign of the Lord's coming, the often breakings forth of fire out of the earth; altho' Hiſtory gives us an account that the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains were fired before Chriſt came. The <hi>Romans</hi> being formerly the afflicters of the natural Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> as ſince they have alſo been of the adopted Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> for which, with their other abominable ſins, the anger of the Lord has been kindled againſt them, yet before the coming of the Lord, it is declared by the Angel to <hi>Eſdras, There ſhall be confuſion in many places, and fire ſhall be oft ſent out again,</hi> 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 5.8.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98071:10"/>which hath lately in a wonderful manner been fulfilled.</p>
               <p>Now all along in the Scripture, the Afflictions of the Natural, and of the Adopted Seed are joyned together; ſo here in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 5. from the beginning to the 14. <hi>verſe,</hi> in a particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner treats of the miſcarriage, and puniſhment of the natural Seed of <hi>Jacob.</hi> And beginning at the 14th <hi>verſe</hi> to the 24th treats of the puniſhment of the adopted Seed of <hi>Jacob.</hi> For in the 16th <hi>verſe</hi> he ſaith, <hi>The Lord of Hoſts ſhall be exalted in Judgment:</hi> At which time the Lambs ſhall feed after their manner. Therefore this is to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled when the Lord again comes: Againſt which time it is ſaid, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Hell hath enlarged her ſelf, and opened her mouth wide without meaſure; and their glory, and their multitude, and their pomp, and he that rejoyceth ſhall deſcend into it.</hi> This doth evidently appear, that Hell hath enlarged her ſelf by theſe often torrents and rivers of Fire, Pitch, and Bitumen, which God hath lately ſent out thence. According to the Word of God in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> Chap. 32. 22. <hi>For a fire is kindled in mine anger, and ſhall burn to the loweſt Hell, and ſhall conſume the Earth with her increaſe, and ſet on fire the foundations of the Mountains.</hi> By theſe words we are to underſtand, that the fire of Hell and the fire in the Foundations of theſe Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains extendeth it ſelf from the one, to the other: This is further treated of in a Book that is to come forth. And it is alſo ſaid in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30. <hi>v.</hi> 30. <hi>For Tophet is ordained of old; yea for the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98071:11"/>King it is prepared, he hath made it deep and large; the pile thereof is fire and much wood, the breath of the Lord, like a ſtream of Brimſtone, doth kindle it.</hi> This Tophet here ſpoken of, is Hell; the King for whom it was prepared, is the Devil; but Man that is inſnared by him does alſo fall into it. For the Lord ſaith, <hi>Depart from me, ye curſed, into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, Matth.</hi> 25.41. But all Hell will not be fired, till the laſt and final Judgment, when all the dead will be judged, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14. And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>The pile thereof is fire and much wood:</hi> That is, much combuſtible matter fit for fuel, as Brimſtone, Pitch, Sulpher, Bitumen, Coperas, and the like. Theſe things the Lord hath ſo placed; and by his breath and command, he hath kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it. And it is ſaid of the Beaſt, and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that after the Lord comes, they were both taken, and caſt alive into a Lake, of fire burning with Brimſtone, <hi>Rev</hi> 19.20. which Lake is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy kindled, into which they ſhall be caſt, which reacheth to the loweſt Hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. VI.</hi> Whirlwinds from the Lord.</head>
               <p>NOW are the Whirlwinds of the Lord gone forth according to the Word of the Lord: <hi>Behold, the Whirlwind of the Lord goeth forth with fury, a continual Whirlwind, it ſhall fall with pain upon the head of the wicked. The fierce anger of the Lord ſhall not return until he hath done it, and until he have performed the intents of his heart: in the latter days ye ſhall conſider, Jer.</hi> 30.23, 24.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98071:11"/>Theſe Whirlwinds are the continual afflictions, wars and commotions which are upon the Earth, which will not ceaſe, till the Lord hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the intents of his heart. Theſe things alſo are ſet down for them that have the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to conſider of, that thereby they may know what the Lord is going about to do, as to underſtand the time of their viſitation. And again it is ſaid, <hi>Come near ye Nations to hear, and hearken ye my people: let the Earth hear, and all that is therein, the World, and all things that come forth of it. For the indignation of the Lord is upon all Nations, and his fury upon all their Armies, Iſa.</hi> 34.1, 2. And of this time the Lord ſaith in <hi>Eſdras; For the Lord knoweth all them that ſin againſt him, and therefore delivereth he them unto death and deſtruction. For now are the Plagues come upon the whole Earth, and ye ſhall remain in them: for God ſhall not deliver you, becauſe ye have ſinned againſt him,</hi> 2 Eſd. 15.26, 27. This being accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> That <hi>theſe Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds of trouble ſhall not ceaſe in the world, until the Lord have performed the intents of his heart;</hi> Which is, in making his Enemies his Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool, and in coming to take his own great Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Reign, and to reſtore his People.</p>
               <p>And the Lord ſaith to his people concerning this preſent time; 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 16.39, 40, 41. <hi>Even ſo ſhall not the Plagues be ſlack to come upon the earth, and the world ſhall mourn, and ſorrow ſhall come upon it on every ſide. O my people hear my word: make ye ready to the battel. And in thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98071:12"/>be even as Pilgrims upon the Earth: He that ſelleth, let him be as one that fleeth away: And he that buyeth, as one that will loſe: He that occupieth Merchandice, as he that hath no profit by it: And he that buildeth, as he that ſhall not dwell therein,</hi> &amp;c. And it is ſaid in the 47. v. <hi>And thoſe that occupy their Merchandice with Robbery, the more they deck their Cities, their Houſes, their own poſſeſſions, and their own perſons, the more I will be angry with them for their ſins, ſaith the Lord.</hi> By this robbery is meant all unjuſt gain, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful dealing with one another.</p>
               <p>And the Lord ſaith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>The lofty looks of man ſhall be humbled, and the haughtineſs of men ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be exalted in that day. For the day of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall be upon every one that is proud and lofty, and upon every one that is lifted up, and he ſhall be brought low.</hi> And the like the Lord ſaith in <hi>Malachy,</hi> Chap. 4.1, 2. <hi>For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the day cometh that ſhall burn as an oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble, and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, that it ſhall leave them neither Root nor Branch. But unto them that fear my Name ſhall the Sun of Righteouſneſs ariſe with healing in his wings, and ye ſhall go forth and grow up as Calves of the ſtall.</hi> And the Lord ſaith, <hi>Mat</hi> 7.19, 21. <hi>Every Tree that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not forth good fruit, is hewen down and caſt into the fire.</hi> And he alſo ſaith, <hi>Not every one that ſaith unto me Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98071:12"/>of Heaven: But he that doeth the will of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> For when the Lord comes it will not ſerve our turns, to ſay; that we believed in his Righteouſneſs for Salvation. But how we have obeyed him, in doing the will of his Father which is in Heaven, that thereby his Righteouſneſs may be imputed to us. <hi>Who is become the Author of Eternal Salvation to all them that obey him, Heb.</hi> 5 9. For now it is not with us, as it was with the Gentiles at their firſt Calling in, who had never heard of Chriſt, nor what he required of them. But it is with us, as it was with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from whom God expected an improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their day and ſeaſon of Grace; the which for their not doing, they were caſt off. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20, 21. <hi>If God ſpared not the Natural branches, take heed leſt he alſo ſpare not thee.</hi> Thereby ſhewing, that we ſtand no ſurer than <hi>Iſrael</hi> did. Therefore he ſaith, ver. 20. <hi>Be not high minded but fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore let all that deſire to have an intereſt in him, humble themſelves under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt them in due time. And the Lord ſpeaking of his ſecond coming, ſaith, 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 6.23, 24. <hi>The Trumpet ſhall give a ſound which when every man heareth, they ſhall ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be afraid</hi> (This every man here doth but ſignifie the greater part, for it will be a time of rejoycing to Saints) 24 <hi>v. At that time ſhall Friends fight one againſt another like Enemies, and the Earth ſhall ſtand in fear with thoſe that dwell therein, the ſprings of the Fountains ſhall ſtand ſtill, and in three
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98071:13"/>hours they ſhall not run.</hi> Which accordingly has been fulfilled concerning the Fountains of Waters, they have already ſtood ſtill, when the great Earthquakes were in <hi>Ciſily.</hi> And alſo it was given as a Sign of the Lord's coming, <hi>that there ſhould be monſtrous Children brought forth,</hi> 2 Eſd. 5.8. Which accordingly in theſe laſt years hath been in ſeveral Nations fulfilled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Signs in</hi> England.</head>
               <p>AS God hath at this time ſhewed forth part of his wrathful indignation in thoſe Nations that worſhip the Beaſt, and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; So in this limited time God hath ſhewed to us marvelous things, in Token of mercy and kindneſs, thereby to awaken us that his coming is juſt at hand; Whereby we might improve our Day and Seaſon of Grace, ſo as to make pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration for his coming; that by ſo doing we might not be condemned with them that will not. And God in a wonderful manner has given us time and ſpace of Repentance, in that he hath given us a King, who hath continued to us our liberty &amp; opportunities of ſeeking God; which had it been otherwiſe, we might have been cut off, before theſe awakening Judgments came, by which the Lord calls to the <hi>Inhabitants of the Earth to learn Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 26.9. So that thereby many might be awakened, and come out of their groſs darkneſs. And alſo all of us, from a vain, and wicked, and looſe Coverſation. Now
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98071:13"/>as the other Nations have had awakning provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God's diſpleaſure, by the Earthquakes, and Fires, that have broken out of the earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, ſo God in a wonderful manner hath appeared amongſt us in the miraculous Cure of four women, which the like was never heard of ſince Chriſt's time. Who in thinking and being perſuaded the Lord was able to Heal them, became healed, Two of an extraordinary lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, one of eighteen years continuance, uſing Crutches; the other having her thigh and ancle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone out of joint from her childhood; And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of a Leproſie; and one of a withered hand from her childhood. Theſe things being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly known, and attefted in the City of <hi>London.</hi> And the Lord having wrought theſe miraculous Cures upon theſe women, it ought to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by us. For as the Lord came by a Woman, ſo after he aroſe, he appeared firſt to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. And now at the time of his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he hath miraculouſly appeared in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of miracles on Women. And alſo another great and evident Sign the Lord hath given us of his coming; and that the great <hi>Jubile</hi> is at hand, by the miraculous ſpringing up of a Field of Corn, without plowing or ſowing, and of that goodneſs and quantity, the like was never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heard of ſince the firſt Creation, when all things ſprang up of themſelves; and this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Crop ſpringing up out of ſixteen Acres of fallow Land, which formerly had been ſown with Turneps. This Miracle was near <hi>Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98071:14"/>in <hi>Kent,</hi> being generally known, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly publiſhed: This Land belonged to a Man that was very charitable to the Poor. Thereby the Lord alſo ſhewing, that in time to come, ſuch will be abundantly rewarded; For he ſaith, <hi>The merciful ſhall obtain mercy,</hi> Matth. 5.7. And <hi>he that giveth to the poor, lendeth to the Lord,</hi> Pro. 19.17. And it is ſaid, <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the waters: for thou ſhalt find it after many days,</hi> Eccleſs. 11.1.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. VIII.</hi> Where the Armies are to be gathered together, after the Lord comes.</head>
               <p>THE Lord ſaith in <hi>Revelations,</hi> ch. 16.15, 16. <hi>Behold, I come as a Thief; bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his garments, leſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame. And he gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them together into a place called in the Hebrew Tongue Armageddon.</hi> Now here in theſe verſes the Lord tells us how he will come; and they are thoſe that will be bleſſed, that are found watching for his coming; and that, when he does come, it is then he will gather together theſe great armies or people <hi>to the place called</hi> Armageddon. And in <hi>Joel</hi> there the Lord calls it the Valley of <hi>Jehoſhaphat; Let the Heathen be wakened, and come up to the Valley of Jehoſhaphat: for there will I ſit to judge all the Heathen round about,</hi> Joel 3.12. Theſe words ſhew, 'tis after they are awakened by the coming of the Lord, that then they will be gathered together to the Valley of <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hat;</hi> for it is there the Lord will ſit to judge
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98071:14"/>the Heathen round about, that have <hi>Iſraels</hi> Land in their poſſeſſion, as in the 3 <hi>Ch.</hi> 2 <hi>ver.</hi> And where this Valley of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> is, is made mention of in 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 20.26 <hi>And on the fourth day they aſſembled themſelves in the Valley of Barachah, for there they bleſſed the Lord: therefore the name of the ſame place was called, the Valley of Berachah unto this day.</hi> And in this Valley <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> bleſſed God for the great deliverance he had given them from their Enemies, which Enemies were thoſe that were related to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> as <hi>Ammon, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab,</hi> and <hi>Mount Seir.</hi> So thoſe that are again to be there gathered, are thoſe that pretend Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Chriſtian Iſraelite;</hi> as Pope, and Turk, and the negligent Chriſtian, all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the true God, but in works deny him, For all the Chriſtians that bear the name of Chriſt of the Gentile race, whether good or bad, are alike term'd Heathen in the Old Teſtament; 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 2.34. For then there being no other than <hi>Jews</hi> and Heathen, they could be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe expreſſed, as I have already by the word proved. Therefore the Lord here ſaith, <hi>Now conſider this ye that forget God, leſt I tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver,</hi> Pſal. 50.22. And alſo accordingly the Lord ſaith to <hi>Eſdras,</hi> that when he comes, it is then they will be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, the which will be to the fore-mentioned place. For at, or about the time of his coming, there will be fighting together in their own Land; As in 2 Eſd. 13.30, 31, 32, 33, 34. <hi>And he ſhall come to the aſtoniſhment of them that dwell
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98071:15"/>on the Earth. And one ſhall undertake to fight againſt another, one City againſt another, one place againſt another, one people againſt another, one Realm againſt another. And the time ſhall be when theſe things ſhall come to paſs. and the ſigns ſhall happen which I ſhewed thee before, and then ſhall my Son be declared. And when all the people hear his voice every man ſhall in their own Land leave the Battle they have one againſt another. And an innumerable multitude ſhall be gathered as thou ſaweſt them wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come, and to overcome him by fighting.</hi> Which fighting here, without doubt, will be like that of <hi>Jacobs</hi> wreſtling with the Angel, which was by prayer for a bleſſing. But they having by their wicked practices (as in the 37 and 38 <hi>verſes</hi>) loſt their day and ſeaſon of Grace, it will with them then be too late, as it was with <hi>Eſau,</hi> to have the bleſſing. All theſe places agree in one and the ſame thing, that there will be fighting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another at or about the time of the coming the Lord; and that it will be after the Lord comes that they ſhall be gathered together to <hi>Armegeddon,</hi> or otherwiſe called the Valley of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> there to be judged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Everlaſting Covenant and Crown of Life.</head>
               <p>THE Everlaſting Covenant and the Crown of Life, is one and the ſame thing. And when the Lord again comes, he will make that new everlaſting Covenant with both the Houſes of <hi>Jacob;</hi> in which Covenant, the true practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98071:15"/>believer will be then included; as coming in by the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> who are now but Heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of the ſame promiſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. And then it is, <hi>they ſhall no more teach every man his Neighbour, and every man his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaying, Know ye the Lord: For they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them, to the greateſt of them, ſaith the Lord;</hi> Jer. 31.34, 35, 36. Then it is, His <hi>People ſhall be willing in the day of his power, in the beauties of holineſs,</hi> Pſal. 110.3. And then it is, <hi>Iſrael ſhall be ſaved in the Lord, with an everlaſting Salvation; They ſhall not be aſhamed nor confounded world without end,</hi> Iſa. 45.17. And then it is, <hi>the Lord will reſt in his love,</hi> Zeph. 3.17. Ezek. 37.26, 27, 28. when <hi>Iſrael</hi> is put into a capacity never more to offend him.</p>
               <p>And then is life crowned to the Soul, when they are thus ſecured by him. And then it is, <hi>that ſighing and ſorrowing will fly away.</hi> And then it is, <hi>The days of his People ſhall be as the days of a Tree, and that his Elect ſhall long injoy the work of their hands,</hi> Iſa. 65.22. And then it is, <hi>The meek ſhall inherit the Earth; and ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light themſelves in the abundance of peace</hi> Pſ. 37.11.</p>
               <p>But the fore-mentioned promiſed new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, will not be made with the reſt of the Nations that then will be called in, as God by the Prophet hath declared, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.61. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the thouſand years when Satan is again looſed, and the eminent glory of the Lord is not ſo viſible among them; then Satan will again draw off ſome of them that are ſpared of thoſe Nations
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98071:16"/>which are not ſecured by the everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; <hi>and fire ſhall come down from Heaven and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</hi> And then <hi>the Devil that deceived them, will then be caſt into the lake of Fire and Brimſtone, where the Beaſt and falſe Prophet are, and ſhall be tormented day and night for ever and for ever,</hi> Rev. 20.3, 9, 10. From which words we are to take notice, the Lord here declareth the continuance of day and night, as alſo in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 89.36, 37. And after the Devil is caſt into Hell, we read of no other than a temporal puniſhment inflicted on them of the Nations, that will not go up to worſhip <hi>the King the Lord of Hoſts and keep the feaſt of Tabernacles,</hi> Zec 14.16, 17. And how many thouſand years it will be after Satan is caſt into the fire of Hell, before the final judgment, the Lord beſt knoweth; But by the word it is clear, it will be many thouſand years. For God hath ſaid, <hi>He will keep Covenant and mercy to a thouſand Generations,</hi> Deut. 7.9. And from <hi>Adam</hi> to this time, we cannot well reckon above a hundred Generations. For where St. <hi>Luke</hi> counts the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogy from <hi>Adam</hi> to Chriſt, he reckons up but about three ſcore Generations, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>And this fore-mentioned Kingdom, is the Kingdom of which the Angel told the bleſſed Virgin, <hi>that Chriſt ſhould Reign over the Houſe of Jacob for ever, and of his Kingdom there ſhall be no end,</hi> Luke 1.33. This <hi>ever</hi> chiefly includes the ever of the world to come; in which time Chriſt will have his Reigning Power, and at the time of the laſt Judgment, when the Heavens and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98071:16"/>Earth are ſaid <hi>to fly away,</hi> Re. 20.11. The fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Book explaineth the meaning thereof; fully making it appear by the word, there is two ſorts of Heavens, and Earth; whereby it is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved, that the Kingdom of Chriſt will have no end; according to the word of the Angel to the Bleſſed Virgin, and according to the word of the Lord in <hi>Daniel; But the Saints of the moſt High ſhall take the Kingdom, and poſſeſs the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for ever, even for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 7.18. And God ſaith in <hi>Iſaiah, For as the New Heavens and the New Earth which I will make; ſhall remain before me, ſaith the Lord, ſo ſhall your Seed and your Name remain,</hi> Iſa. 66.22. For then it is, God will give <hi>Iſrael</hi> a place of their own, ſo as they ſhall move no more, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.10.</p>
               <p>But we not apprehending there is <hi>three Evers, three Times, three Generations,</hi> and <hi>three Worlds</hi> ſpoken of in Scripture, thereby we have been much in the dark concerning this world to come. And this world to come being the time that is chiefly comprehended in <hi>Pſal:</hi> 89.2. <hi>For I have ſaid, mercy ſhall be built up for ever, thy faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhalt thou eſtabliſh in the very Heavens. I have made a Covenant with my Choſen, I have ſworn to David my Servant. Thy Seed will I eſtabliſh for ever, and build up thy Throne to all Generations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. X.</hi> The Meaning of the Feaſt of Tabernacles being again kept.</head>
               <p>NOw in that the feaſt of Tabernacles is again to be kept, when all the other great
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98071:17"/>Feaſts are laid aſide, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.16. it doth thereby appear, that when <hi>Iſrael</hi> and thoſe of the Nations which are ſaved are firſt gathered, they will then again for ſome time dwell in booths, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did when they came out of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this feaſt to be kept for a remembrance in the <hi>ever</hi> of the time to come. But ſome may ſay, How can the Nations come up yearly to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> the Journy being ſo far diſtant from ſome? But none need Queſtion but God will make them of ability to do what he requires of them.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>That every one that is left of all the Nations.</hi> That is, every one of the Nations that were left ſhould go up yearly to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but not that it is there meant that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very individual perſon of the Nations will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to go up year by year unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but ſome of the heads of the Nations. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid in the 18 verſe, <hi>If the Family of Aegypt go not up,</hi> &amp;c. Then a National puniſhment is threatned.</p>
               <p>Now what we find written in the old and new Teſtament, and nothing therein to contradict the plain meaning thereof, that will of certain be fulfilled in the plain and clear way, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. But that is a figurative Speech, and not to be taken in the letter of the word, where we find other Scriptures in contradiction to it. There God hath a ſecret vail'd in it, which he reſerves until ſuch time as he will have it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed.</p>
               <p>But that God commands to be done; And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98071:17"/>what God declares he will have done; And what God hath ſworn he delights not in; And what God hath abſolutely promiſed to do; And what God hath ſworn he will do; Theſe things are to be taken as they are expreſt, or we are apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatized from the truth.</p>
               <p>And it is at the Reſtauration of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that the Everlaſting Covenant will be eſtabliſhed, as to which time, God has ſworn to <hi>Iſrael, That he will not be wroth with them, nor rebuke them any more,</hi> Iſa. 54.8, 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>For then God will put his fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from him,</hi> Jer. 32.39, 40, 41. And concerning that time, <hi>The Lord hath ſworn by his right hand, and by the arm of his Strength, that he will no more give their Corn to be meat for their enemies, neither ſhall the Sons of Strangers drink the Wine for which they have laboured,</hi> Iſa. 62.8. This promiſe will be fulfilled <hi>when Jeruſalem is made the praiſe of the earth,</hi> as in the 7th <hi>ver.</hi> Which is at the time of the Reſtitution of all things when the Lord again comes, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20, 21, 22, 23, 24. And then it is, <hi>There ſhall come out of Zion the Deliverer, and ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from Jacob,</hi> Rom. 11.26. Iſa. 59.20. <hi>Then ſhall the Lord rore out of Zion, and utter his voice from Jeruſalem, and the Heavens and Earth ſhall ſhake, but the Lord will be the hope of his People, and the Strength of the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.16. This <hi>Zion,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is meant of the glorious Tabernacles ſpoken of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.2.</p>
               <p>But we all coming out of the Darkneſs of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, have loſt the right apprehenſion of this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98071:18"/>Kingdom or World to come, whereby we are involved in great miſtakes, ſo as to think the promiſed everlaſting Covenant is now eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that ſuch as belong to it may fall foully, but not finally; but when that Covenant is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed; then it is <hi>that God will put his fear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hearts, ſo as they ſhall never depart from him,</hi> Jer. 32.40. But we, not underſtanding aright this Kingdom or World to come, which has been the cauſes of turning the plain word of God in the old Teſtament into figurative Speeches, and thereby made the Oath and Promiſe of God to <hi>Iſrael</hi> void; Of which St. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts the Church <hi>to take heed to the ſure Word of Prophecy, as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place,</hi> 2 Peter 1.19.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> Where the Great Glory of the Lord will be, when he comes to deliver his people.</head>
               <p>WHEN the Lord again comes to deliver his People, his infinite glory will then again be in the Clouds, in which will be thoſe glorious manſions, into which he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his raiſed Saints, <hi>John</hi> 14.2, 3. and there will be that <hi>Tabernacle which the Lord ſhall pitch, and not man,</hi> Heb 8.2. which will be over the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> from whence he will deſcend to <hi>Mount Olivet,</hi> and alſo from the Tabernacle he will deſcend upon <hi>Mount Zion,</hi> and there will he <hi>make the place of his feet glorious,</hi> Iſa. 60.13. For as the Lord formerly deſcended down in a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98071:18"/>Cloud into the Tabernacle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 40.34. So the Lord will again deſcend upon <hi>Mount Zion.</hi> And as the Lord was over <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Clouds, when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was drowned in the Sea, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.19, 20, 24. So again the Lord will be in the Clouds when the Beaſt, and falſe Prophet ſhall be taken alive, and caſt into a lake of fire burning with Brimſtone, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.</p>
               <p>And as the King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> with all their Prognoſticators and Diviners, could not by them have any knowlege of their near approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ruine; So will it be with thoſe in our days; for they will not foreſee the near approaching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſſedneſs or miſery; according to the word of the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.25. <hi>The Lord fruſtrateth the Tokens of liars, and maketh Diviners mad, that turneth wiſe men backward, and maketh their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge fooliſhneſs,</hi> This will again be alike at the time of <hi>Jacobs</hi> deliverance.</p>
               <p>And it is ſaid of Chriſt in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.1. <hi>Oh that thou wouldeſt rent the Heavens, that thou wouldeſt come down, that the Mountains might flow down at thy preſence.</hi> V. 4. <hi>For ſince the beginning of the World men have not heard, neither perceived by the Ear, neither hath the eye ſeen, O God! beſides thee, what he hath prepared for him that waiteth for him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2 9. Pſalm 31.19. And oh! that there might be many amongſt us, and elſewhere found, ſuch as are true waiters for him, ſo as thereby to become the bleſſed of the Lord, and not found as the fruitleſs Fig-tree, which of the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the curſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98071:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XII.</hi> The Fruitleſs Fig-Tree.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MARK</hi> 11.13. <hi>And Jeſus ſeeing a Fig-tree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off, having leaves, he came, if haply he might find any thing thereon: and when he came to it, he found nothing but leaves, for the time of figs was not yet.</hi> This Fig-tree was the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the body or generality of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> on whom the Lord when he came, found nothing but leaves only; The which was only an outward ſhew and Form of Religion, having nothing of real holineſs, and of upright walking amongſt them, as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.23, 24, 25, 26.27, 28. For tho' the time of ripe fruit, as Figs, were not yet, yet there might have been green Fruit, as ſincerity, and an upright and holy converſation. But as for <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s bearing ripe fruit, it was not to be in this time, but in the time to come, after the <hi>ever</hi> of this time is paſt and gone. Then it is they will be made partakers of the continual freſh ſprings of the Spirit of God, which is <hi>drinking of the River of his pleaſures,</hi> Pſal. 36.8. For then they will have an Inherent perfect righteouſneſs, and that ſecured by the eſtabliſhing of that now-promiſed <hi>new-everlaſting Covenant,</hi> which will crown Life to the Soul, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.17. <hi>But Iſrael ſhall be ſaved in the Lord, with an everlaſting Salvation: ye ſhall not be aſhamed nor confounded world without end.</hi> For the everlaſting covenant when eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Crown of Life is one and the ſame thing, only two ways worded. And the Believer
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98071:19"/>comes in by Chriſt as Heir to that promiſed Covenant, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28, 29. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. But the Believer in Chriſt is no longer a Believer, than he believes Salvation is to be had, according to the tenour of the Goſpel (which is in the way of our love and obedience) no more than a Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man is a Righteous man in the day that he comitteth iniquity, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XIII.</hi> Concerning the Remnant and firſt Churches; and alſo the World.</head>
               <p>BUT whereas the remnant and firſt Churches were fore-choſen of God according to the Counſel of his own will for the purpoſe he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined for them, which was to bear their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the truth, and for the glory that ſhould follow. And tho' they were not thus fore-cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, for their fore-ſeen willing and running; yet afterward when they had embraced the Faith, they were to run for the price, for the hopes ſake that was ſet before them, which is the Crown of Life, which was to be obtained by their wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and running, by which way it is to be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all that will lay hold on it. For when the Goſpel was eſtabliſht, we that followed after were to take to the way, and keep the Rule ſet before us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. And the Lord will be with us in his way, and never forſake any while they keep his way by walking in a holy and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Converſation. And all that know the Lord by the Goſpel, ſhould go to him for ſtrength, for he hath promiſed his aſſiſtance.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98071:20"/>
               <p>Now after the world was convinced that Chriſt was the Son of God, they were put into a capacity of obedience, as man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as have the call of the word, and the good motions of the Spirit of God, therefore if afterward they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried, it was thro' their own negligence, and barrenneſs of the Soil into which the Seed of the word was caſt, according to the Parable of the Lord, <hi>Ma.</hi> 13.20, 21. which brought forth Fruit for a time, and afterward withered away,</p>
               <p>For when the Lord had laid the World under a Conviction by the which means it was part of the world embraced the Faith and brought, forth-Fruit, according as it did in the Church of <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> Col. 1.6. And the Lord laid <hi>Iſrael</hi> under a conviction when he ſhewed them his glory in the Wilderneſs, and gave to them his Laws and Statutes <hi>Exod</hi> 19.9, 16, 18. And when God would have healed <hi>Babylon,</hi> it was by bringing her under a conviction, in pulling her great Monarch down from his Throne, and making him eat Graſs like the Oxen, till his hairs became like Eagles feathers, and his Nails like Birds Claws, and he made to acknwledge to all Nations, that the Great God of Heaven ruleth over the Children of men, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.33. <hi>ch.</hi> 3.29. Now when God hath convinced his Creatures, he takes delight to ſee them improve that rational underſtanding that he hath given them to their Souls advantage, and then it is according to their willing and running they ſhall find accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98071:20"/>with him, and accordingly be rewarded by him. And the people are condemned, not becauſe they knew not God, but becauſe they had no will to obey him; as in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.30, 31. <hi>They would have none of my counſel: they deſpiſed all my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof. Therefore ſhall they eat of the fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices.</hi> And the Lord ſaith to the Jews, <hi>John</hi> 5.40. <hi>Ye will not come to me that ye might have life.</hi> Thereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the door of mercy was wider open to them of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> than they were willing to embrace and improve the opportunity. And oh that we would not, as they were, be found alike guilty, and ſo be made partakers of the more ſeverer vengeance. But on the contrary, that we would turn from all our evil ways, and <hi>ſeek the Lord while he may be found, and call upon him while he is near,</hi> Iſa. 55.6, 7. begging his aſſiſtance, that we may be able to withſtand all our corrupt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and inclinations; and if we are ſincere therein, God will not be wanting to us. But if we have no love to his ways, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. nor will not obey him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.30. and will not chuſe his fear, <hi>verſe</hi> 29. then for ſuch, there remains no hope: For we ſhall ſtand or fall, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as we chuſe or refuſe obedience to his will. Now, we through the miſtaking of ſome of the ſayings of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> have made the Oath of God, and the general Call and Offer of mercy by Chriſt to all that will, according as it is tendred, lay hold of it, to be of no effect. Notwithſtanding St. <hi>Peter</hi> fairly warns us, that in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98071:21"/>were ſome things hard to be underſtood; which ſome did wreſt to their own deſtruction, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. And could we no otherwiſe have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the meaning of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> than in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction of the God of Truth, it had been a far leſs errour to have thought St. <hi>Paul</hi> might have erred, than to have made the Oath of God, and the general offer of mercy by Chriſt, void, by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehending the words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo as to think that none but the Elect could be ſaved. But as the Prophet, for believing the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the contradiction of what God himſelf had ſaid, therefore was deſtroyed; for a Lion met him and ſlew him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13.17, 18, 19, 23, 24, This being ſet down for a warning to us, that we might not be alike guilty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XIV.</hi> What the Sign is when God for Sin intends to leave a Nation, People, or Perſon. And the Kingdom of God in this time, and the Kingdom of God in time to come, explained.</head>
               <p>VVHen God becauſe of Sin, determines to leave a People, Nation, or Perſon to deſtruction, he then leaves them to deluſion, and to blindneſs of mind, like as <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.20, 21. and <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 81.11, 12. And Chriſt ſpake to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rables; <hi>That by hearing, they ſhould hear, and not underſtand; and ſeeing, they ſhould ſee, and not perceive,</hi> Matth. 13.14. For the Jews were then in expectation of the coming of the glorious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98071:21"/>Kingdom of God, which was foretold them by the mouth of all the Prophets; and therefore a <hi>Phariſee demanded of Chriſt, when the Kingdom of God ſhould come. And he anſwered him, and ſaid; The Kingdom of God cometh not with obſervation,</hi> [but more rightly expreſt, as it is ſet down in the Margin of your Bibles, not with ſhew] <hi>neither ſhall they ſay, lo here, or lo there, for behold the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God is within you,</hi> Luke 17 20, 21. Chriſt, by theſe words ſheweth, that in this time, he was but to have his ruling-power in the hearts of his People. And by this it is clear, it is thoſe that he rules in that are his. And this being the only viſible Kingdom that God has in the time of this World; which Kingdom or People, is not in ſhew of this World's greatneſs and grandeur. This anſwer of the Lord, was quite contrary to what the Phariſee expected; for he only appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the Lord was to come to Reign, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore all things, and not that he was firſt to come to ſuffer; and this proved a ſtumbling-block to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Lord ſaid in the following verſes to his Diſciples of his ſecond coming, <hi>v.</hi> 23, 24, 25. <hi>For as the lightning that lightneth out of the one part under Heaven, ſhineth unto the other part under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo ſhall alſo the Son of Man be in his day.</hi> For the glory of that day will be ſuch, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> terms the then time but night, to that approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing day, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12, 13.</p>
               <p>And Chriſt concerning the Parable of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming and Kingdom, ſaith, <hi>Matth. c.</hi> 13.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98071:22"/>
                  <hi>v.</hi> 41, 42, 43. <hi>The Son of Man ſhall ſend forth his Angels, and they ſhall gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, and them that do iniquity. And ſhall caſt them into a Furnace of Fire: there ſhall be wailing, and gnaſhing of teeth. Then ſhall the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> Here the Lord declareth the time of the end of this World will be, when he cometh, at which time, the Power of this World will be taken from them, by his coming and ſending <hi>his Angels to gather out of his Kingdom all things that offend, and them that do iniquity.</hi> By theſe words, nothing can be more plain, than that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which will then be Chriſt's, is this material World, from which, thoſe that offend, and do ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, will then be caſt out. Now from theſe words alſo, the Lord leaves himſelf ſcope, to take in thoſe that are given him of his Father at his ſecond coming, the which alſo will be his Elect, which is <hi>Iſrael, Rom.</hi> 11.28. and other Nations mentioned in the Word, which will then be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and then will the way of the Kings of the Eaſt be prepared, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.12. And the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Book ſheweth, whom the Lord hath ſaid ſhall likewiſe be ſpared; and all theſe will be brought to a ſenſe of their own unworthineſs, and ſo lay hold of mercy, before the wicked is deſtroyed, and therefore then they will not be offenders, when the wicked are caſt out; ſo as the Lord may take in whom he will of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; and God will as well keep faithful to his promiſe at Chriſt's ſecond coming, <hi>in calling in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98071:22"/>the Jews and others with them,</hi> Iſa. 56.8. as he did perform his promiſe to Chriſt when he firſt came, in calling in, and juſtifying the ſinners of the Gentiles.</p>
               <p>And in that Chriſt ſaith to his Diſciples, in the 43th verſe; <hi>Then ſhall the righteous ſhine forth as the Sun, in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> Here Chriſt doth not ſay, all the righteous; therefore he hath his reference to the raiſed Saints, and the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that will be caught up in the clouds into thoſe glorious Manſions or Tabernacles, which the Lord pitcheth, and not Man, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.5, 6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.21. From which, they ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father. In this portion, hath the Diſciples their part; and when the Kingdoms of this World, are become the Kingdoms of our God, and of his Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. Then it is that the Kingdom of this World, is become the Kingdom of their Father, into which they ſhall thus gloriouſly ſhine forth; and this is that the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. likewiſe <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.4. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.6, 7. and then they ſhall have their reigning-power on the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. next under Chriſt their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head. Now the Lord all along whilſt he was upon the Earth, ſpake but in Parables as to his ſecond coming and Kingdom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.34. by reaſon <hi>Iſrael</hi> being ſinful, for which it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of God, they ſhould be left to blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer by them; for tho' in other things they ſinned wilfully, yet they ignorantly crucified the Lord of Life, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98071:23"/>
               <p>And the Lord again ſpeaking of his ſecond coming, and of gathering the Nations; and by the Parable of ſetting the Sheep on his right hand, and the Goats on his left; <hi>He ſaith to them on his right hand, come ye bleſſed of my Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom prepared for you from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World,</hi> Matth. 25.34. Now from the foundation of the material Heavens and Earth, there was no other Kingdom prepared but this World, which will be again reſtored. But the Law and Goſpel ſpeaking but to thoſe that are under it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. and <hi>chap.</hi> 2.12, 14. The Lord might therefore have his reference to the foundation of the World that was laid in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for the World to come; at which foundation, Chriſt was figuratively ſlain in the Paſchal Lamb: And then was the Kingdom of <hi>Canaan</hi> prepared for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by their Enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And the Gentiles that Chriſt ſhall find in obedience amongſt the Chriſtian Nations at his coming, will then be made the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritors with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of this Kingdom. For they were not only to be Heirs with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of the promiſed Everlaſting Covenant, whereby Eternal Life is ſecured to the Soul; but they were alſo to have a ſhare with them in their Inheritance: For of <hi>Japhet</hi> it was propheſied, that he ſhould dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem;</hi> and therefore this Kingdom may likewiſe be ſaid to be prepared for them: And alſo at the reſtoration of all things, it is that <hi>Iſrael</hi> will be reſtored to their own Land, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.16. <hi>And then will God make her Wilderneſs
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98071:23"/>like Eden, and her Deſart like the Garden of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 51.3. And then it is Chriſt will have his peaceable Kingdom, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.9. <hi>They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountain: for the Earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea,</hi> Iſa. 65.23, 24, 25. <hi>And in that day God will make a Covenant for them, with the Beaſt of the Field, and with the Fowls of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and with the creeping things of the ground; and he will break the Bow, and the Sword, and the Battel out of the Earth, and will make them lie down ſafely,</hi> Hoſea 2.18, 19. <hi>And then will God betroth them unto him for ever in righteouſneſs, and in judgment, and in loving-kindneſs, and in mercies,</hi> v. 19. And then, this is the Peace the Lord hath declared ſhall be in the time of his Kingdom. But when Chriſt firſt came, he ſaid, he came <hi>not to ſend Peace on Earth, but a Sword,</hi> Matth. 10.34. For in this time, them that are the true Followers of Chriſt, the Devil will be ſtill raiſing them up Enemies. And Chriſt ſaith to his Diſciples, <hi>That in him, they might have peace; but in the World, they ſhould have tribulation,</hi> John 16.33. And likewiſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That after his departure, ſhall grievous Wolves enter in among them, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Flock. And alſo of their own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples after them,</hi> Acts 20.29, 30. which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly followed.</p>
               <p>Now whereas it is ſaid, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.7. <hi>When a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, he maketh his Enemies to be at peace with him.</hi> This King <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpake
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98071:24"/>of the natural Seed of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> which had they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the fear of the Lord, they had then been the Emblem of that peaceable Kingdom that is now to come: And they in this time ſhould have been the Head, and not the Tail, and above only, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.13. But there never was any ſuch promiſe made to the true Churches of Chriſt in this time; but on the contrary, they were foretold they ſhould be afflicted, perſecuted, and meet with fiery Tryals; neither were they to adorn themſelves, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XV.</hi> The Elect Church diſcovered. And why God ſuffered the Beaſt to ariſe to deceive the Nations. Alſo a twofold being in the Book of Life.</head>
               <p>NOW Chriſt by his Word declareth that he would have an Elect Church or People throughout this World, that ſhould never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Beaſt, or falſe Prophet. And that it was to his Diſciples which came of the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unto whom Chriſt promiſed to be with to the end of the World, <hi>Matth.</hi> 38.20. And that none ſhould pluck them out of his hand. And tho' the firſt Gentile Churches that received the Word from the mouth of the Diſciples, were likewiſe alſo Elected, and fore-choſen of God, and made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt; yet their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Generations, were but raiſed to that from which <hi>Iſrael</hi> fell. And God foreſeeing that the Gentile Nations that embraced the Goſpel, would afterward fall away, by having no love to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98071:24"/>Truth, but taking pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the People of Old had done, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 22. therefore it was determined of God they ſhould be left to ſtrong deluſions to believe a Lye: Becauſe they received not the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. For which cauſe it was the determination of God, that all that dwell upon the Earth ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Beaſt, whoſe names are not written in the Book of Life, of the Lamb ſlain from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7, 8. That is, all the Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations that dwell upon all the Earth, that the Beaſt had dominion over, ſhould worſhip him, except thoſe whoſe Names were written in the Book of Life; for the Word ſpeaks to them that received it, and it was thoſe fell into the ſnare, that had not a love to it, but took pleaſure in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And <hi>Luther</hi> ſays, that the Beaſt, and falſe Prophet, are generally comprehended under one head, And the Lord ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8. <hi>And they that dwell upon the Earth ſhall wonder, whoſe names were not written in the Book of Life from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World, when they behold the Beaſt.</hi> Now, I have already proved by the Word in a Treatiſe concerning Election, that there was no Election through the firſt World of People, nor till after the miſcarriage of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Then did the Lord ſecure a certain rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of them to himſelf, at which time <hi>Iſrael</hi> was laid for the foundation of the World to come; for all that come in as Heirs to that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98071:25"/>World, come in as the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and from that foundation, Chriſt was figurative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlain in the Paſchal Lamb; and from that foundation, were the works of thoſe unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Jews finiſhed that fell in the Wilderneſs when they refuſed to go to fight for the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And becauſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s miſcarriage, the firſt Gentile Churches were choſen to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Holy Ghoſt, and to bear their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the Truth; the which are ſaid to be <hi>choſen before the foundation of the World,</hi> which foundation was <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the which choice, was not before them as to matter of time, but as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of choice and liking in God, rather to make choice of them that ſhould ignorantly offend him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>han them that had wilfully diſobeyed him. And I alſo have proved, that the Eternal Purpoſe, has only a relation to the Eternity that lies before us; that the being choſen from the beginning, was no other, than from the beginning of the Preaching of the Goſpel. And I have alſo proved, that the Decree was made, that the Entrances into Life ſhould be made ſtrait, after <hi>Adam</hi> fell, and how that ſtraitneſs doth conſiſt: And what is meant, by being of old ordained to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. And alſo I have proved in the Book in which the Faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> is explained, that them of the World embraced the Faith, in the Apoſtles time, and brought forth fruit, as it did in the Elect Churches. All theſe things I have made clear, which hitherto we have not rightly underſtood, which makes me the oftener recite them.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98071:25"/>
               <p>Theſe things being proved, it makes it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that there was none Elected from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation but the remnant. And alſo the firſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Churches that were afterward Elected were long departed this life, before the Beaſt aroſe, ſo as there was none of them then to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him.</p>
               <p>Now there is alſo a twofold way of being in the Book of Life. Firſt, They that have their names there. Secondly, Thoſe that have a part therein, and it is thoſe that have their names there, that are Elected and fore-choſen. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt Gentile Churches were called in, their Children were taken into Covenant, and a Door of Mercy ſet open to all ſuch as would take hold of the offer of Life according as it is tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt. Now if theſe have not their names put into the Book of Life when they are taken into Covenant, yet they have their part in the Book of Life, in performing the conditions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Life is offered by Chriſt (for thoſe he will juſtifie by his Righteouſneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9.) The which name or part in the Book of Life, may not only be loſt through negligence and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs, but by adding or diminiſhing from the Word, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.19. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2. And there are others alſo that have a part in the Book of Life, which will find Redemption in the World to come; for they were ſuch as received not the Truth in the love of it, but took pleaſure in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, that the Apoſtle ſaith ſhould be damned, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.12. And they were ſuch as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98071:26"/>heard the Truth, and would not believe to obey it, that the Lord gave Sentence againſt. But thoſe that have had a longing deſire after the Truth, and ſuch as have not taken pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, ſuch will find Redemption in the World to come. And no young Children can take pleaſure in iniquity: Therefore when all come to be judged according to their works, ſuch will be cleared, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. But I ſhall not here inſiſt upon this Subject, becauſe I intend hereafter fully to prove it. But by what the Lord ſaith, it is of dangerous conſequence to take from the Word, as well as to add unto it.</p>
               <p>Now the Gentile Chriſtians, when they came to have no love to the Truth whereby they might be ſaved, but on the contrary, took pleaſure in iniquity, God gave them up to worſhip the Beaſt; for when they would not be bound with the Cords of his Laws, and follow him in Love, Patience, and Humility, in expectation of the reward of the Crown of Life, when the Lord again ſhall come; then it was God permitted the Prince of Darkneſs to ſet up his pretended Kingdom, by which deluſion they alſo loſt the apprehenſion of the glorious Kingdom of Chriſt, which is now to come, and is very nigh at hand, which Kingdom has been foretold by all the Prophets, ſworn to by God himſelf, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.2. declared by the Apoſtles: And becauſe the Lord Chriſt ſpake but in dark Sentences and Parables, when he was upon the Earth, becauſe that <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98071:26"/>being ſinful thereby might be blinded: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he declared in Viſion to St. <hi>John,</hi> how he would come, and of the glory of the New <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> that ſhould come down from Heaven, and of his reigning Power here upon the Earth, Alſo annexing thoſe great threatnings mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19. to any that ſhould add or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh to the words of this Prophecy.</p>
               <p>Now all the Gentile Chriſtians thus falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deluſion, ſo as when any of them come out of that darkneſs by the knowledge of the Word, it was evident to them, they could not be of that remnant that ſhould never be deceived, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon themſelves knew, that they, or their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had been deceived by the Beaſt; but as to that Remnant, Church or People, that the Word does thus bear witneſs to, I ſhall not here ſpeak further of; but hereafter, by God's aſſiſtance, I ſhall declare who the Two Witneſſes are, and then I ſhall make appear who this Church, and People, and Remnant are, to whom the Word doth thus bear witneſs to, and they to the Word: Whilſt on the contrary, the Apoſtate Church, or great Harlot, bear not witneſs to the Word, nor the Word to her, any otherwiſe than to her condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And our Predeceſſors being all involved in that darkneſs, whereby we have loſt the true ſentiments of the Word, and ſo miſtakingly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all that was ſaid to the firſt Churches, and to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at the reſtitution of all things, as tho' they now belonged to us, the which is of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence, and whereby many like <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98071:27"/>feed on wind. And the Ordinances that were to be kept as they were delivered, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. never came to our hands, by reaſon of which, every one hath placed their Faith and Church Government according to their ſeveral Opinions; in which all reſt confident that they are in the right; the which begets in many a hatred one to the other. And now we are in diviſion, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> was when the Lord firſt came; and the Chriſtians being raiſed to that from which <hi>Iſrael</hi> fell, and falling into ſin, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did, whereby the ſecond coming of the Lord, has been as little underſtood by us, as his firſt coming was by them. For the Prince of this World coming, which had no part in Chriſt, and the Nations of the World which had em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the Goſpel, again forſaking the Lord, and following after the Prince of Darkneſs; was therefore termed by the Lord, <hi>The Prince of this World;</hi> which Prince had no part in the Redemption purchaſed by the Lord, but the People of the World had, till they forfeited their Bleſſing, by having no love to the Truth, and by taking pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, and ſo loſt the knowledge of the Word by the Beaſt ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it; by reaſon of which, the World again became over-ſpread with Darkneſs, the Remnant Elected, only retaining the truth of the Word, or true Light. But the Lord of his mercy, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the end of the Reign of the Beaſt, cauſed Light to break forth, &amp; ſo made choice of <hi>Luther</hi> for that end, to bring the Goſpel again much to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98071:27"/>Light, ſo as the People might, by the call of the Word, lay hold of the tender of Grace in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of Everlaſting Life.</p>
               <p>And now according to the Promiſe of God, at the end of the time, the Viſion ſhould ſpeak, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3. hath now cauſed the true meaning of his Word to break forth, that the great ſecrets therein contained might be revealed: But before the end of the time the word that <hi>Daniel</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of, was from him cloſed up and ſealed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.9. God ſaid, <hi>Go thy way Daniel: for the words are cloſed up and ſealed till the time of the end.</hi> And in <hi>verſe</hi> 4. <hi>Thou, O Daniel, ſhut up the words, and ſeal the Book, even to the time of the end: many ſhall run to and fro, and knowledge ſhall be increaſed;</hi> likewiſe <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.7. <hi>But it ſhall be one day which ſhall be known to the Lord, not day, nor night: but it ſhall come to paſs that at evening time it ſhall be light.</hi> Now the Lord hath won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully cauſed the true meaning of his Word to break forth, whereby we may prepare for the coming of the Lord, and come out of all our miſtakes, and from a looſe and vain converſation before the ſevere Vengeance falleth, that we may not be made partakers thereof. And therefore he hath given us the knowledge of his coming, for he is a merciful High-Prieſt, having compaſſion on them that are unwillingly out of the way; but them that love their Opinion, Pleaſure, or Profit, more than their God, or took up their Religion for by-ends; it is ſuch will remain in Darkneſs, by reſiſting the Truth. But let all
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98071:28"/>have a care they fall not into the ſnare, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did; for when the Lord firſt came, he coming not of a Perſon of Dignity, but of one of no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in this World; This proved a ſnare to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:</hi> Let us take warning by them, and not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the owning of the truth; for if we do, we ſhall be taken in the ſnare as they were: for the day of the Lord will come as a ſnare upon all them that will not prepare for him, and take the warning given by him, by the ſigns, and the opening of the word, as he hath declared, and now made them manifeſt to the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The difference between the State of the Elect in this time, and of that which is to come.</head>
               <p>NOW when God does Elect, or fore-chuſe any Perſon, or perſons, it is not only to be an advantage to themſelves, but alſo to carry on the Counſel of the will of God in the purpoſe he hath determined; As the Remnant for a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding witneſs. The firſt Churches likewiſe to partake of the Holy Ghoſt, and to bear their teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony to the truth of the Goſpel. And alſo they were to withſtand the fury of the enemy, and to meet with fiery tryals. Theſe things were ſo certainly alotted here their portion, that they were not to think ſtrange of it; <hi>Pet.</hi>— neither are <hi>Iſrael</hi> that will be taken in and be the Lords Elect in time to come, choſen only for themſelves, but alſo to carry on the Counſel of the will of God, that the other Nations that are ſpared might be bleſſed in them, who are given to <hi>Iſrael</hi> for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98071:28"/>Daughters and Servants; Who in ſome meaſure will partake of the glory: And alſo in this time, if God doth elect or chuſe any ſingle perſon, it is not only for the benefit of that perſon, but to carry on the Counſel of the Will of God. As <hi>Joſiah,</hi> he was to break down the Altars of the falſe Gods. And <hi>Cyrus,</hi> to reſtore <hi>Iſrael</hi> to their own Land. And <hi>Luther,</hi> to bring the Goſpel again to light, that others that would, might take hold of the offers of mercy.</p>
               <p>I hope that His Majeſty, and the Great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of the Nation will take theſe things into their conſideration, that thro' their incouraging the Knowledge of the truth, it may meet with better ſucceſs than it did in <hi>Swedeland.</hi> For when the good Miniſters that truely feared God, ſeeing the Signs the Lord foretold ſhould be before his coming, and thereby apprehending his near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, was willing to acquaint the people, that thereby they might prepare for the coming of the Lord, ſo as they might not be found in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at that day; and that day come upon them at unawares. But the greater part withſtood the truth, like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, and would ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Knowledge of it, and preſently ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the Miniſters in <hi>Holland</hi> to continue as they were. The certainty of this came over in the Monthly Mercury.</p>
               <p>And I alſo heard by an Outlandiſh Miniſter, that when the good Miniſters of that Country, upon the ſigns the Lord had given of his coming, and they knowing there was a great deal of the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98071:29"/>Scripture unrevealed, therefore deſired that they might joyn in earneſt prayers to the Lord for the right underſtanding of his word; and to leave off their Scholaſtick way of preaching, and more to ſtudy the Word. But thoſe that were in the wrong, being the ſtrongeſt party would not yield thereunto.</p>
               <p>But I hope our Miniſters, and Teachers, of all Parties, will not follow their Example; ſince it is made ſo clearly evident, that the ſtroke will fall on the Chriſtians, that ſhall be found in darkneſs at that day. And ſince we have been all in miſtakes, ſome more, and ſome leſs, till God of his mercy, now again brought the true meaning of his word to light, according to his promiſe, as we therefore may the better pity and pray one for the other; and by a ſpeedy refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, break off from our ſins by working righteouſneſs, and in ſhewing mercy to the poor who are at this day languiſhing: And alſo by our owning the whole truth, that thereby w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may unite and ſerve the Lord with one conſent And that by us the Proteſtant Churches beyond Sea might be warned; and that by our and their owning the whole truth, it may give ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm to the Chriſtian World, that many Millions of Souls might come out of Darkneſs. For the Lord giveth his Creature an opportunity to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, and this being now the ſmall time that is given the Chriſtians, whereby to eſcape the wrath to come, if we accordingly take hold of it, and do not ſtand in oppoſition againſt the truth.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:98071:30"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
